Mehdi Azad

✓ m32abbas@uwaterloo.ca

SUMMARY: 8+ years experienced Machine Learning and Systems Design with a strong background in software development, specializing in computer vision, robotics, and natural language processing.

- Developed and deployed ML and data pipelines and software solutions for biotech and healthcare.
- Led the creation of a biotech device prototype, resulting in a high-impact publication and a US provisional patent.
- Proficient in multiple programming languages and frameworks including Python, Java, PyTorch, OpenCV, and HPC.
- Experienced computer science instructor, teaching data structures & algorithms, data science, and object-oriented programming

KEY SKILLS

(Generative) AI/ Computer Vision/ Machine Learning/ Reinforcement Learning/ Robotics/ NLP/LLM/ Data Science/ Systems Design/Statistical Modeling/MLOps/DevOps/Cloud Computing

EDUCATION

MEng in Systems Design Engineering | University of Waterloo

2019 - 2020

Specialization: Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning

MSc in Engineering | Iran University of Science and Technology

2004 - 2007

BSc in Engineering | Isfahan University of Technology

2000 - 2004

Work Experience

Research Scientist/ Instructor | George Brown College

Jan 2024 - Present

School of Computer Technology

- Investigated application of protein language models (pLMs) in protein design and engineering
 - Employed LLMs to (1) predict active sites and mutation effects of antibodies, and (2) generate useful antibody sequence
- Courses: Applied Data Science/ Data Structure and Algorithm/ Object-Oriented Programming

Machine Learning Scientist | SickKids Hospital

May 2021 - Nov 2023

AI researcher in a team of experimental and computational neuroscientists

- Built a biotech device automating pain testing in mice (resulting in a high-impact publication and a US provisional patent)
 - Applied ML pipelines for computer vision-based object detection and real-time tracking with 0.01mm accuracy
 - Performed system design and built the prototype of motion tracking robot to solve poor reproducibility and low throughput problem of manual pain testing
- Proposed a novel and reproducible metric to evaluate pain behavioural response in mice
 - Designed experiments and collected/cleaned data and pioneered in quantifying non-reflexive behaviors
 - Drawn meaningful patterns from behavioural precise data through exploratory data analysis/visualization and developed ML model to predict the data

Data Scientist | University of Waterloo, Spafford Neurobiology Lab

SEP 2019 - Aug 2020

Systems design engineer focusing on solving life science problems

- Pioneered in capturing electrophysiological signal emanating from living micro organisms
- Effectively communicated research findings to both technical and non-technical audiences

Control Systems Consultant | Energy Industries Engineering & Design (EIED)

SEP 2014 - FEB 2017

Control systems consultant in natural-gas refinery plants systems design

- Supervised and approved intelligent control system algorithms to ensure compliance with requirements
- Collaborated with multidisciplinary teams to test the functionality of packages for distributed control systems

Control Systems Software Developer | PoyaKar - Manufacturing Co.

May 2010 - Aug 2014

Control engineer leading mechatronics systems design

• Developed software to achieve precise motion control in CNC machines with 5 μ m accuracy

Technical Skills

Programming Language: Python/Java/SQL/Scala

Frameworks & libraries: PyTorch/ Apache Spark/ Scikit-learn/ Pandas

Tools & Technologi: High Performance Computing (HPC) / AWS / Git & GitHub / Docker / Kubernetes